A Guide to the John S. and James L. Knight Foundation records, Printed Material, RG 8 FA1802
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Articles and Clippings, 1954-2015; 2; 2.14 Cubic Feet 4 containers
  - Clippings, 2008 March 4-October 17 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Includes news articles on a Knight Foundation grant to Duluth to support sustainable economic and social growth; a $1.05 million grant for Habitat for Humanity of the Mississippi Gulf Coast; the opening of the Newseum in Washington, DC; an interview with Trabian Shorters re: social entrepreneurship; an editorial re: a OneCommunity grant for Milledgeville; the Knight Commission on the Information Needs of Communities in a Democracy; and the establishment of the BioInnovation Institute in Akron, Ohio with help from a $20 million grant from KF. Also included are Knight News Challenge Media Clips, which includes blogs.
  - Clippings, 2009 July 19-November 30 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 4578
    Articles and blogs downloaded from the KF Intranet: Office Chatter. Includes an article about a KF grantee, Spot.US; a speech by Paula Ellis; a blog entry concerning foundation-supported journalism; articles re: city of Milledgeville winning a grant from KF for digital upgrades and censorship at Google; the Knight Arts blog; a story on the debut of "Final Edition: Journalism According to Jack and Jim Knight", a documentary on the Knight brothers; and an article (in Spanish) re: Knight Foundation grants with the Knight Arts Challenge in Miami for $3.7 million. Dennis Scholl is quoted in the article.
  - Clippings, 2010 August 29-December (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 4818
    Full page ad in Biloxi Sun Herald re: rebuilding of gulf communities after Hurricane Katrina and featuring a photo of KF staff and trustees volunteering with Habitat for Humanity; ads re: Knight Arts Challenges in Miami and Philadelphia; article in Pulse about Knight's support of cutting edge artists in Miami and a small article in the newsletter of Art Basel, the Miami Beach arts festival, features the Knight Arts Challenge and a picture of Alberto Ibarguen. KF announced the 2010 winners at Art Basel.
  - Articles and Clippings, 2011 January 20-June 5 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 4826
    Articles and blogs downloaded from the KF Intranet. Includes a New York Times article on Random Acts of Culture program supported by KF; and an article, "Glass Half Full" re: 2011 Knight Open Government survey finds freedom of information change but many agencies lag in following Obama's openness order; Miami Herald article re: Artistic Explosion in Miami re: KF's private/public partnership and the Knight Arts Challenge. Also included are ads re: Journalism and Media Grant Making publication, and ads re: Knight Arts Challenges in Miami and Philadelphia.
  - Random Acts of Culture, 2011 Summer (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 4931
    Article in Philanthropy magazine about the Knight Foundation and its art program, Random Acts of Culture. Features information about the Knight brothers (with photographs) and the Knight Foundation. Dennis Scholl is interviewed. (2 copies of magazine)
  - Articles and Clippings, 2014 October 3 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Knight File Number - 5457
    USA Today Snapshot: "Most Important First Amendment Right". The source was the KF survey of students and teachers.
    Restricted - Open in 2025.
  - My Year with Knight by Brian Brackeen, 2014 January 7 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 5293
    Blog post from The Starting Gate details how KF has impacted Brian Brackeen's start-up company, Kairos.
  - Articles and Clippings, 2015 March 24-May 12 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Knight File Number - 5601
    Articles re: Online platform "Open Humans"; Twitter; Take-Action Buttons; and Growing a Non-Profit News Site.
    Restricted - Open in 2026.
  - Miami Today: Best of Miami 2015, 2015 June 4 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Knight File Number - 5572
    Miami Today special issue features KF Trustee Susan Kronick, Dennis Scholl and Victoria Rogers for their work with the arts; Miami Program Director, Matt Haggman, for improving the quality of life in Miami; and Lilly Weinberg as an "unsung hero". (2 copies).
  - Matt Haggman: Building Miami Entrepreneurs at Knight Foundation, 2015 June 11 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Knight File Number - 5571
    Miami Today cover story featuring Miami Program Director, Matt Haggman (2 copies).
  - Have Museum - Will Travel: Bringing Artwork to the People, 2015 August 31 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Knight File Number - 5569
    The Chronicle of Philanthropy article on the KF sponsored Inside Out art program in Detroit which places replicas of master artworks outdoors. The article mentions a $2 million KF grant to bring the program to Miami, Philadelphia and Akron.
  - Theaster Gates Takes Art to the Bank, 2015 October 1 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Knight File Number - 5583
    Chicago Reader cover story about KF grantee, Theaster Gates, and a project of his Rebuild Foundation, which turned an old bank building into public art spaces.
  - John Shively Knight, 1894-1981: A Tribute to an American editor by the Akron Beacon Journal, 1981 June 1 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
    Knight File Number - 2458
    Akron Beacon Journal memorial booklet published June 1981 in tribute to John S. Knight. Contains photos, biographical information on Knight and his family, tributes by leaders of the Akron business community and newspaper industry and readers, details on the Knight Foundation, honors and awards received by Knight, and his memorial service. (2 copies, plus 4 reprints).
  - Wheels of Fortune: A History of Rubber in Akron - Who Runs Akron? A New Style of Leadership, 1997 November 30 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Knight File Number - 2459
    Akron Beacon Journal produced a yearlong look at the rise and fall of Akron's rubber industry. Week 48 focused on the tire company executives and the Beacon Journal's John S. Knight who were "Akron's primary movers and shakers during the industry's heyday." Also included is an article on the level of Knight Foundation giving to Akron. Quoted are: John Ong, Gerald Austen, C.C. Gibson, and Ben Maidenburg. (2 copies)
  - Akron Beacon Journal - "John S. Knight is Dead at 86", 1981 June 17 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Knight File Number - 2460
    Akron Beacon Journal front page obituary of John S. Knight, who died June 16, 1981 at the age of 86.
  - Slow Growth at the Biggest Foundations, 2006 March 23 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Knight File Number - 3703
    The Chronicle of Philanthropy article on foundations features a picture and caption of KF president, Alberto Ibarguen, in Biloxi after Hurricane Katrina. Ibarguen is quoted in the article and KF's relief efforts described.
  - Akron Beacon Journal - "Proud Past, New Dawn", 2006 April 26 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Knight File Number - 3775
    Akron Beacon Journal special section about its legacy and history of 100 years under the Knight name. The McClatchy chain, which bought Knight Ridder in 2006, sold the paper in June 2006. Included in the special section is an article on the influence of John S. Knight and a historical timeline.
  - How Detroit Was Reborn, 2014 November 9 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 5481
    Sunday Detroit Free Press newspapers (2 copies) with multiple stories about Detroit's rise from bankruptcy and the Grand Bargain engineered, in part, by the Knight Foundation and trustee Mariam Noland. Also included is a note to Alberto Ibarguen from Paul Anger, Editor of the Press.
  - 50th Anniversary of Knight Foundation Commemorative Articles and Ads, 2000 June 11 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Knight File Number - 3848
    Akron Beacon Journal special section about The Knight Foundation at 50, which includes a history of the Foundation and the Knight brothers and highlights of grants made. Also included are full page ads in the Miami Herald and the Sun-Sentinel of South Florida on the occasion of KF's anniversary.
- Publications, 1992-2020; 3; 2.31 Cubic Feet 5 containers
  - Hurricane Andrew: The Big One, 1992 January (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 1690
    Soft cover book, "Hurricane Andrew: The Big One." Photographs by the staffs of the Miami Herald and El Nuevo Herald, 1992. Some of the photographs in this book were used in the 1992 Annual Report.
  - Arts Funding: A Report on Foundation and Corporate Grantmaking Trends and Arts Funding Revisited, 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 2693
    Soft cover book, Arts Funding: A Report on Foundation and Corporate Grantmaking Trends (1993) and Arts Funding Revisited (updated, 1995). A comprehensive study of grantmaking trends, it was based on research conducted by the Foundation Center with support and collaboration of Grantmakers in the Arts. The Knight Foundation was one of the foundations participating in the research study. Also included is an update to the report and highlights.
  - The Decay of America's Cities: A Call for Leadership, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 2652
    Soft cover book, The Decay of America's Cities: A Call for Leadership, was published by the American Press Institute. It is the edited proceedings of the J. Montgomery Curtis Memorial Seminar. The Seminar is supported by endowment funds provided by the Knight Foundation. KF Trustee, James Batten, was a featured speaker. The book includes photos, biographical information and the text of his speech.
  - Lessons Learned from Hurricane Andrew, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 2519
    Conference proceedings. The conference was sponsored by a grant from the Knight Foundation.
  - Redland: A Preservation and Tourism Plan, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 2520
    Published by the Metropolitan Dade County Office of Community Development Historic Preservation Division and the University of Miami School of Architecture with a grant from the Knight Foundation. The Redland is an agricultural area of South Dade County and was hard hit by Hurrican Andrew.
  - Community Foundations in the United States: 1992 Status, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 4006
    Soft cover book, "Community Foundations in the United States: 1992 Status", prepared by the Council on Foundations from survey data.
  - The Governor's Forum: Engaging in a Civil Society: Report and Recommendations, 2000 June 6 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Knight File Number - 4007
    "Engaging in a Civil Society" is a report and recommendations from a statewide conference on building strong partnerships of government, business and the nonprofit sector to address Florida's needs in the 21st century. Hodding Carter, Penny McPhee and Larry Meyer participated.
  - Arts Survive: A Study of Sustainability in Arts Education Partnerships, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 8-10)
    Knight File Number - 2386
    Soft cover book, Arts Survive: A Study of Sustainability in Arts Education Partnerships by Steve Seidel, Meredith Eppel, Maria Martiniello of Project Zero, Harvard Graduate School of Education. The Arts Survive Research Study was supported by the Knight Foundation. (3 copies)
  - American Journalism in Transition: A View at the Top, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 3845
    American Journalism in Transition: A View at the Top. A Report of the Fifth Annual Aspen Institute Conference on Journalism and Society by Amy Korzick Garmer. This is a summary of the conference, which featured Hodding Carter as speaker and participant. The conference was sponsored by the Knight Foundation.
  - Covering the Education Beat: A Current Guide for Editors, Writers and the Public, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 2725
    Note-book publication (binder cover removed), Covering the Education Beat: A Current Guide for Editors, Writers and the Public. Prepared by the National Education Writers Association, this resource guide provides advice, source material, and background materials. The guide was produced with funds from the Knight Foundation.
  - Plugged In: Using the Internet for High School (and Professional) Journalism, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 4866
    Softcover book. Distributed by the Radio and Television News Directors Foundation and supported by KF.
  - Evaluating Community Collaborations, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 2726
    Hardback book, Evaluating Community Collaborations, edited by Thomas Backer. The book is the "first comprehensive treatment of theoretical, research and practice issues concerning the evaluation of collaborations." It includes a chapter on the Knight Foundation's Youth Violence Initiative authored by Knight consultant Nancy Guerra and commentary by John Bare.
  - Journalism, Security, and the Public Interest: Best Practices for Reporting in Unpredictable Times, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 4872
    Softcover book. A report of the Seventh Annual Aspen Institute Conference on Journalism and Society. It features a forward prepared by Eric Newton. Newton and Alberto Ibarguen participated in the conference, which was partially supported by KF and put on by The Aspen Institute.
  - Philanthropy in the Sunshine State, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 3377
    Softcover booklet prepared by the Florida Philanthropic Network, which presents a comprehensive look at Florida's grantmaking foundations and donors. Includes information on KF, ranked number 1 in assets in the state of Florida. Hodding Carter served on its board of directors.
  - Plugged In: Using the Internet for High School (and Professional) Journalism; Second Edition, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Knight File Number - 4868
    Softcover book. Distributed by the Radio and Television News Directors Foundation and supported by KF. Updated version of the 2002 book.
  - Digital Future Initiative: Challenges and Opportunities for Public Service Media in the Digital Age, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 4869
    Softcover book. A report by the DFI panel, of which Alberto Ibarguen served as an ex officio member.
  - Overtown: Men's Health Study, 2006 May (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Knight File Number - 4870
    Softcover book. A report by the Collins Center for Public Policy and partially funded by KF. The report detailed the results of a study of men's health in the Overtown section of Miami, FL.
  - Risk Map for Journalists: Brazil - Colombia - Mexico by IAPA, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Knight File Number - 3799
    Softcover book prepared by the Inter American Press Association with support by the Knight Foundation. Knight Foundation's support (over 4 million dollars since 1997) is mentioned, as are significant KF personnel. The publication serves to document the violence against journalists in the three countries and alerts and educates journalists on the dangers inherent to news coverage in those countries.
  - A Platform for Participation and Innovation: Smart Communities in Chicago Master Plan, 2009 December (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Knight File Number - 5200
    By LISC/Chicago. The master plan is part of the City's Digital Excellence Initiative aimed at demonstrating the value of technology to those who don't currently use it, improving access to technology tools and helping to create a 21st century digital infrastructure citywide.
  - Austen BioInnovation Institute in Akron, c. 2009 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Knight File Number - 4682
    Brochure describing the Institute, which was named for retired chairman, Gerald Austen, and supported by KF (3 copies).
  - Seeking Sustainability: A Nonprofit News Roundtable: Summary & Report, 2010 April 26 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Knight File Number - 5202
    Report came out of a roundtable discussion, hosted by KF, and featuring several KF speakers, on how non-profit journalism programs can move beyond the support of foundations and wealthy individuals and find sustainability.
  - Media, Information Systems and Communities: Lessons from Haiti, 2010 May 24 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Knight File Number - 5201
    Report came out of a roundtable discussion, hosted by KF, and discusses how new applications, such as SMS (short message service), texting, interactive online maps and radio-cell phone hybrids, were used to aid disaster recovery operations. Also includes a copy of the report translated into French and also into Creole.
  - What's Next for Philanthropy, 2010 July (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 4871
    Softcover book. A report by the Monitor Institute. Acting Bigger and adapting better in a networked world. Co-authored by Barbara Kibbe, a featured speaker at a KF staff retreat. Mayur Patel is listed as a contributor. (3 copies)
  - Center for Investigative Reporting: California Watch Year One Evaluation: Executive Summary, 2010 December (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 5054
    Softcover book. California Watch produces investigative and enterprise stories that are distributed to news partners across all platforms. It is supported by KF. (3 copies)
  - American Public Media's Public Insight Journalism Year One Evaluation Report, 2010 December (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 5055
    Softcover book. Public Insight Journalism is a new model of journalism designed to bring together public engagement, the knowledge-sharing power of the internet, and high journalistic standards. It is supported by KF. The report was prepared by the LFA group. (2 copies)
  - City Success: Theories of Urban Prosperity, c. 2010 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 5203
    Softcover book. Choosing the right path to success is one of the most important decisions urban leaders will make. City Success is a comprehensive review of the principal theories of urban success divided into three categories: Theories of Firms, Theories of People, and Theories of Place by Joseph Cortright, Impresa Consulting and supported by CEOs for Cities and KF.
  - National Public Radio: Knight Training Evaluation, 2011 January 21 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 5056
    Softcover book. TCC group was hired to measure the direct impact of NPR's Knight Training Program on newsroom operations, determine what worked, and identify best practices. (2 copies)
  - Evaluation of the Knight Case Studies Initiative, 2011 February (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 5057
    Softcover book. The Knight Case Studies Initiative was launched in February 2007 to enhance the way journalism is taught by applying the Case Method of instruction to the field of journalism. KF hired metis associates to produce an evaluation of the project. (2 copies)
  - Jefferson Institute's Military Archives Project in Serbia: From Ruins of War, a Nation's History Pre, 2011 March 14 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Knight File Number - 5059
    Reporter's analysis by Joan McQueeney Mitric and Djordje Padejski, details the results of a $50,000 seed money grant from KF to the Jefferson Institute to design a system to convert the Yugoslavian military's 40 million paper documents into searchable, digital format.
  - Connected Citizens: The Power, Peril and Potential of Networks, 2011 Spring (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 5205
    Softcover book. Forward written by KF which asked the Monitor Institute to take a critical look at the role of networks in community life. The resulting essay was written by Diana Scearce.
  - Mississippi Renewal Forum Rebuilding Efforts, 2005-2006 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 4351
    Four publications: 1) Summary Report: Recommendations for Rebuilding the Gulf Coast; 2) A Pattern Bok for Gulf Coast Neighborhoods: Details and techniques for building and renovating Gulf Coast houses. KF grants have supported this rebuilding process, particularly in Biloxi, MS. 3) New York Times Magazine article (May 21, 2006), "Battle for Biloxi" critical of the rebuilding efforts. KF is mentioned. 4) "Rebuilding the Gulf Coast: Mississippi Renewal Forum: October 12-17, 2005: schedule and articles of interest on participants.
  - One Laptop Per Child Association Newsletter, 2012 Summer (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 5753
    Features article, "Principal Walker's Reaction to OLPC at Miami Holmes Elementary School," about KF grant to a Miami elementary school. Article includes a photograph of George Martinez, Alberto Ibarguen, and former KF trustee Dave Lawrence. KF was listed as an OLPC institutional partner.
  - The Pulitzer Prize Photographs: Capture the Moment, 2011 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 5306
    Softcover book. Featuring Pulitzer prize winning news photos from 1942-2011. Eric Newton edited the book. A traveling exhibit of the photos, supported by KF, was on display at the Frost Museum, FIU in 2014.
  - Evaluation of the Ashoka News and Knowledge Program, 2011 February 7-March 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 5058
    Softcover books. Three reports produced by LFA Group: Evaluation of the Ashoka News & Knowledge Program, Final Report; Ashoka News & Knowledge Program, Fellow Snapshots; and Case Studies of Four Ashoka Fellows.
  - A Report on the Carnegie-Knight Initiative on the Future of Journalism Education, 2011 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 5204
    Softcover book. The Carnegie-Knight initiative was developed to "advance the US news business by helping revitalize schools of journalism" through curriculum enrichment, News21, and the Carnegie-Knight Task Force. This book reports on the initiative and its outcomes at eleven journalism schools.
  - Great Expectations: Macon Speaks, 2011 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 4974
    Softcover book. A report by the Fanning Institute. KF provided partial support for a public engagement survey of Macon, Georgia residents. Focus groups and neighborhood meeting participants voiced their concerns and priorities in anticipation of the upcoming local elections.
  - Conducting a Scan of Your College Access and Success System, c. 2011 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 4981
    Softcover book. Why it matters. How to do it. How to use it. By Victoria Dougherty and Michele Lempa of the OMG Center for Collaborative Learning. The case study research, conducted in Miami and Philadelphia, was funded by KF. 3 copies
  - 2012 BME Leadership Award Winners: Share, Inspire, Empower (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 4995
    Softcover booklet presents the winners of the Black Male Engagement (BME) challenge in Detroit and Philadelphia. Each winner has a brief profile, photo, project description, and contact information. 6 copies
  - 2013 BME Leadership Award Winners: Share, Inspire, Empower (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Knight File Number - 5199
    Softcover booklet presents the winners of the Black Male Engagement (BME) challenge in Detroit, Baltimore and Philadelphia. Each winner has a brief profile, photo, project description, and contact information. 3 copies
  - Perez Art Museum Miami (PAMM), 2013 December (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 5291
    The former Miami Art Museum, now the Perez Art Museum Miami opened its new waterfront facility in December 2013. It features a Knight Plaza which will link PAMM to the Frost Museum of Science and a Knight Education Center, designed to support innovative education programs. Included are brochures for PAMM and the Knight Schools Program; and two photos of the plaza with a note from Alberto Ibarguen to trustees and staff (and replies from Paul Steiger and Frank Borges).
  - FIU Foundation 2012-2013 Annual Report (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Knight File Number - 5292
    Florida International University Foundation Annual Report features a story about KF's commitment to the school and a photo of Alberto Ibarguen posing with the alumni of the school on the staff.
  - Clusters and Your Economy, 2014 January (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Knight File Number - 5602